<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Abouts on PG Drange</title>
    <link>http://drange.net/about/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Abouts on PG Drange</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2017 20:00:16 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://drange.net/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>about</title>
      <link>http://drange.net/about/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2017 20:00:16 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://drange.net/about/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;current-status&#34;&gt;Current status&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m Pål Grønås Drange, researcher in the the Algorithms group, Department of
Informatics, University of Bergen, Norway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I received my PhD from the University after defending my thesis &amp;ldquo;Parameterized
Graph Modification Algorithms&amp;rdquo;, which was supervised by Professor Fedor
V. Fomin. My scholarship during the PhD period came from Fomin&amp;rsquo;s ERC Advanced
Grant Rigorous Theory of Preprocessing, ERC Advanced Investigator Grant 267959.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a PhD student from January 2012 until January 2016. October 5th I handed
in my PhD thesis, Parameterized Graph Modification Algorithms and defended this
thesis December 10, 2015. See the press release Kunsten å avdekke strukturer i
komplekse nettverk (Norwegian) and the disputas announcement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From February until May 2015, I visited &lt;em&gt;Serge Gaspers&lt;/em&gt; at NICTA, Sydney and
UNSW in Sydney, Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;research-interest&#34;&gt;Research interest&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main interest is algorithmic graph theory, parameterized complexity,
preprocessing (in the form of kernelization and width parameter analysis) and
exact (sub-)exponential algorithms. Especially for graph modification problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A graph modification problem is a problem where you are given a graph G and a
budget k and you are asked to transform G to some specific target class (usually
a graph class characterized by either forbidden minors, or forbidden induced
subgraphs), modifying at most k vertices or edges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graph classes of particular interest are graphs related to chordal graphs, or
graphs omitting P4, C4, C5 or 2K2 as induced subgraphs. Graph classes of these
types include (pseudo-)split, threshold and chain graphs, trivially perfect and
cographs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of results, we have given subexponential exact algorithms for Trivially Perfect
Completion, Threshold Completion, and Pseudosplit Completion. (STACS 2014)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have shown that Trivially Perfect Editing is NP-hard and does not have a
subexponential algorithm unless ETH fails, but that it, on the positive side,
admits a polynomial kernel (preprint at arXiv).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have shown that Threshold Editing and Chain Editing are NP-hard, but that on
the positive side, they admit quadratic kernels and subexponential algorithms(to
appear). The quadratic kernels also hold for the completion and deletion
variants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a slightly different type of problem, in the area of graph vulnerability, we
showed that Vertex Integrity is NP-complete, on cocomparability graphs (even on
co-bipartite graphs), thereby refuting a twenty year old conjecture, and that
Component Order Connectivity can be solved in lkn time, where l is the size of
the largest connected component in the target graph and k is the budget. (ISAAC
2014)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we showed that there is a single-exponential linear time constant
factor approximation for computing the treewidth of a graph, i.e., we can in
time O(ctn) time obtain a 5-approximation of the treewidth of an input graph
G. (FOCS 2013) Research resources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;orcid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;arxiv&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dblp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cristin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-coauthors&#34;&gt;My coauthors&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hans Bodlaender&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Markus S. Dregi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fedor V. Fomin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stephan Kreutzer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daniel Lokshtanov&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marcin Pilipczuk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Michał Pilipczuk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Felix Reidl&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saket Saurabh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fernando Sánchez Villaamil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R. B. Sandeep&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Somnath Sikdar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jan Arne Telle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pim van &amp;rsquo;t Hof&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yngve Villanger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;education&#34;&gt;Education&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a PhD from the Algorithms group at the Department of Informatics,
University of Bergen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My bachelor and master degree both come from the University of Bergen, with a
short stay at the ILLC at the University of Amsterdam. In 2009, I finished my
bachelor degree in Cognitive science and in 2011, I completed my master thesis
Epistemic Effectivity: Neighborhood Semantics for Coalitional Ability and Group
Knowledge under the supervision of Professor Thomas Ågotnes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>